The basic function underlying a normal distribution, aka a Gaussian,
正态分布  又名高斯分布  其函数本质上
is e^(-x²).
是 e 的 -x² 次方
But you might wonder "Why this function?"
你是否思忖过  为何是这个函数？
Of all the expressions we could dream up that give you some symmetric smooth graph
我们能想到很多个  图像对称光滑  质量集中的函数
with mass concentrated towards the middle,
why is it that the theory of probability seems to have a special place in its heart
但为什么  能在概率论的核心占据一席之地的  偏偏是它呢
for this particular expression?
For the last many videos, I've been hinting at an answer to this question
在前面好几期视频中  我提示了这一问题的答案
and here we'll finally arrive at something like a satisfying answer.
现在  我们终于可以得到较为满意的结论了
As a quick refresher on where we are -
快速复习一下我们的进度
a couple videos ago, we talked about the Central Limit Theorem
上几期视频我们讨论了中心极限定理
which describes how as you add multiple copies of a random variable,
描述的是  如果你把多个同类的随机变量相加
for example rolling a weighted die many different times
比如说  多次摇同一个偏心骰子
or letting a ball bounce off of a peg repeatedly,
或者是让球在钉板上弹了许多次
then the distribution describing that sum
那么  描述该分布的和  似乎会趋近于正态分布
tends to look approximately like a normal distribution.
What the Central Limit Theorem says is
中心极限定理说明了
as you make that sum bigger and bigger under appropriate conditions,
在适当条件下  随着总和越来越大
that approximation to a normal becomes better and better.
总和  会越来越近似于正态
But I never explained why this is actually true,
但我没有解释这为何成立
we only talked about what it's claiming.
我们之前只讨论了它陈述了什么
In the last video,
上期视频
we started talking about the math involved in adding two random variables.
我们先讨论了随机变量相加所涉及的数学知识
If you have two random variables each following some distribution,
如果两个随机变量分别符合某些分布
then to find the distribution describing the sum of those variables,
你想求出两变量之和的分布
you compute something known as a Convolution between the two original functions.
就需要计算两函数的“卷积”
And we spent a lot of time building up two distinct ways
我们花时间构建了两种不同的思路
to visualize what this convolution operation really is.
来形象地展示  卷积操作究竟是什么
Today, our basic job is to work through a particular example which is to ask
我们今天要研究一个特定的例子：
what happens when you add two normally distributed random variables
把两个正态分布的随机变量相加  会发生什么
which, as you know by now, is the same as asking
你已经知道  这个问题等同于
what do you get if you compute a convolution between two Gaussian functions.
计算两个高斯函数的卷积  会得到什么结果
I'd like to share an especially pleasing visual way
我想分享一种很棒的直观的方式  来考虑这个计算
that you can think about this calculation
which hopefully offers some sense of
希望能让你从中了解到
what makes the e^(-x²) function special in the first place.
函数 e 的 -x² 次方的独特之处
After we walk through it, we'll talk about how this calculation is
之后  我们将讨论  该计算是证明中心极限定理的其中一步
one of the steps involved in proving the Central Limit Theorem,
it's the step that answers the question of
这一步回答的关键问题是
why a Gaussian and not something else is the central limit.
为何只有高斯分布  才是中心的极限
But first, let's dive in.
好  我们进入正题
时轴   贰鼠
翻译   NetaP495L  瑞达勒  ZSC
校对   博美子  䶭
The full formula for a Gaussian is more complicated than just e^(-x²).
高斯函数的完整公式比 e 的 -x² 次方复杂很多
The exponent is typically written as - 1/2 (x/σ)²,
指数通常写为 - 1/2 乘以 (x/σ)²
where σ describes the spread of the distribution,
其中 σ 描述了分布的分散程度
specifically the standard deviation.
即标准差
All of this needs to be multiplied by a fraction on the front
所有这些  需要在前面乘以一个分数
which is there to make sure that the area under the curve is 1
以确保曲线下的面积为 1
making it a valid probability distribution.
使其成为有意义的概率分布
And if you want to consider distributions that aren't necessarily centred at 0,
如果你想考虑那些  中心不一定为 0 的分布
you would also throw another parameter, µ into the exponent like this.
你还需要在指数中加入另一个参数 µ   如上所示
Although for everything we'll be doing here, we just consider centred distributions.
不过接下来  我们只考虑以 0 为中心的分布
Now, if you look at our central goal for today,
不妨想想我们今天的核心目标
which is to compute a convolution between two Gaussian functions,
要计算两个高斯函数之间的卷积
the direct way to do this would be to take the definition of a convolution -
最直接的方法就是根据卷积的定义
this integral expression we built up the last video
即上个视频中构建的积分表达式
and then to plug in for each one of the functions involved
然后把高斯函数  分别带入积分中的两个函数项
the formula for a Gaussian.
It's kind of a lot of symbols when you throw it all together
把一大堆符号摞在一起属实有点复杂
but more than anything working this out is an exercise in completing the square
但说白了  这一团计算只是配方法的一道练习题
and there's nothing wrong with that.
直接计算也没什么毛病
That will get you the answer that you want
你一样能得到你所期望的答案
but of course you know me, I'm a sucker for visual intuition
当然了  你也知道我这个人钟情于直观可视化
and in this case,
这个问题  有另一种有趣思路  我之前没在别处见过
there's another way to think about it that I haven't seen written about before
that offers a very nice connection to other aspects of this distribution
它非常巧妙地联系上了高斯分布的一些细节
like the presence of π and certain ways to derive where it comes from.
比如 π 的出现  以及推导 π 的一些方法
And the way I'd like to do this is by first
我打算用一种新颖的方法来解释
peeling away all of the constants associated with the actual distribution
首先我们将实际分布中的常数  通通丢掉
and just showing the computation for the simplified form e^(-x²).
计算的过程中只用简化的 e 的 -x² 次方
The essence of what we want to compute
我们实际想要得到的
is what the convolution between two copies of this function looks like.
是这函数的两个副本的卷积结果
If you remember, in the last video,
回想一下  在上个视频中
we had two different ways to visualize convolutions
我们有两种方法来可视化卷积
and the one we'll be using here is the second one involving diagonal slices.
而我们在这里要使用的  是涉及对角切片的第二种方法
And as a quick reminder of the way that worked,
快速复习一下这种方法的流程
if you have two different distributions
如果你有两个分布
that are described by two different functions, f and g,
概率密度函数分别为 f 和 g
then every possible pair of values that you might get
那么从这两个分布进行采样时  可能得到的每一对的值
when you sample from these two distributions
can be thought of as individual points on the x-y plane.
都可以被视为 xy 平面上的一个点
And the probability density of landing on one such point, assuming independence,
假设两个分布相互独立  落到这一个点附近的概率密度
looks like f(x) times g(y).
像是 f(x) 乘以 g(y)
So what we do is we look at
让我们来看一下
a graph of that expression as a 2-variable function of x and y
这个关于 x 和 y 的二元函数的图像
which is a way of showing the distribution of all possible outcomes
当我们从两个不同的变量进行采样时
when we sample from the two different variables.
它能显示所有可能结果的分布
To interpret the convolution of f and g evaluated on some input s,
要看出 f 和 g 的卷积在某个输入 s 上的几何意义
which is a way of saying
即  有多大可能得到这样一对样本  使得总和为 s
how likely are you to get a pair of samples that adds up to this sum, s,
what you do is you look at a slice of this graph over the line x + y = s
你应该查看该图像在直线 x + y = s 上的切片
and you consider the area under that slice.
并考虑该切片下的面积
This area is almost but not quite the value of the convolution at s.
这个面积差不多但不完全等于在 s 处的卷积值
For a mildly technical reason, you need to divide by √2.
由于一个略为专业性的原因  还需要除以 √2
Still, this area is the key feature to focus on.
总之这个面积是需要留意的关键特征
You can think of it as a way
你可以把它当作
to combine together all the probability densities
把「一定总和下对应的所有结果」的概率密度组合起来
for all of the outcomes corresponding to a given sum.
In the specific case where these two functions look like e^(-x²) and e^(-y²),
在这个实例中  两函数分别是 e 的 -x² 次方和 -y² 次方
the resulting 3D graph has a really nice property that you can exploit.
得到的三维图像具有非常好的特性  值得加以利用
It's rotationally symmetric.
即  旋转对称性
You can see this by combining the terms and noticing that
合并指数后你能观察到
it's entirely a function of x² + y².
指数项完全是关于 x² + y² 的函数
And this term describes the square of the distance
这项描述了「xy 平面上任意一点到原点的距离」的平方
between any point on the xy-plane and the origin.
So in other words, the expression is purely a function of the distance from the origin.
换句话说  这个表达式纯粹是与原点距离有关的函数
And by the way, this would not be true for any other distribution.
顺便提一下  这个特性不适用于任何其他分布
It's a property that uniquely characterizes bell curves.
这个特性  还可以唯一刻画出钟形曲线
So, for most other pairs of functions,
所以对于其他大多数的函数对
these diagonal slices will be some complicated shape that's hard to think about
这些对角切片将是一些复杂的形状  很难理解
and honestly, calculating the area would just amount to
老实说  计算曲线下面积  本质上就等同于
computing the original integral that defines a convolution in the first place.
拿一开始定义卷积的积分  去直接求解
So, in most cases, the visual intuition doesn't really buy you anything.
因此通常来说  这种直观可视化并没有太大的好处
But in the case of bell curves, you can leverage that rotational symmetry.
但是对于钟形曲线  你可以巧用这种旋转对称性
Here, focus on one of these slices over the line x + y = s for some value of s.
这里  固定 s 值  注意直线 x + y = s 的切片
And remember, the convolution that we're trying to compute is a function of s.
记住  我们要计算的卷积是关于 s 的函数
The thing that you want is an expression of s that tells you the area under this slice.
你想得到一个关于 s 的表达式  来告诉你该切片的面积
Well, if you look at that line, it intersects the x-axis at (s, 0) and the y-axis at (0, s)
那条线在 x 轴上的交点是 (s, 0)   在 y 轴上的交点是 (0, s)
and a little bit of Pythagoras will show you that
运用勾股定理就能算出
the straight line distance from the origin to this line
原点到这条线的直线距离
is s divided by √2.
等于 s 除以 √2
Now, because of the symmetry, this slice is identical to one that you get rotating 45°
而由于对称性  这个切片等同于 45° 角旋转后的切片
where you'd find something parallel to the y-axis the same distance away from the origin.
这时它与 y 轴平行  与原点的距离同样是 s/√2
The key is that computing this other area of a slice parallel to the y-axis
关键是  计算平行于 y 轴的切片的面积
is much much easier than slices in other directions
比计算其他方向上的切片面积要简单得多
because it only involves taking an integral with respect to y.
因为只涉及到对 y 进行积分
The value of x on the slice is a constant.
这个切片上的 x 值是一个常数
Specifically, it would be the constant s/√2
具体而言  x 都等于 s/√2
So, when you're computing the integral, finding this area,
因此当你在通过积分  去求面积时
all of this term here behaves like it was just some number and you can factor it out.
这一项都只是一个数值  你可以将其提取出来
This is the important point -
这一点非常重要
all of the stuff that's involving s is now entirely separate from the integrated variable.
所有和 s 有关的项  现在都与积分变量完全分开了
This remaining integral is a little bit tricky.
剩余的这个积分有点棘手
I did a whole video on it. It's actually quite famous.
它其实很出名  我之前有一整期来讲它
But you almost don't really care.
但你真的不用太在意这个
The point is that it's just some number.
毕竟答案只是一个常数
That number happens to be √π
数值恰巧是 l√(pi)
but what really matters is that it's something with no dependence on s.
真正重要的是  它与 s 的取值无关
And essentially, this is our answer.
这实际上就是我们的结论
We were looking for an expression for the area of these slices as a function of s
我们之前在找  以 s 表示切片面积的函数表达式
and now we have it.
现在已经找到了
It looks like e^(-s²/2), scaled by some constant.
它看起来像是 e 的 -s²/2 次方乘以某常数
In other words, it's also a bell curve,
换句话说  这仍是一个钟形曲线
another Gaussian just stretched out a little bit because of these 2 in the exponent.
只是由于指数中的 2  它被拉伸了一点
As I said earlier, the convolution evaluated at s is not quite this area.
就像我之前说过的  卷积在 s 处的值并不完全等于这个面积
Technically, it's this area divided by √2.
严格来说  卷积等于这面积除以 √2
We talked about it in the last video but it doesn't really matter
我们在上一个视频中提到过  但倒也不重要
because it just gets baked into the constant.
毕竟归给后面的常数就好
What really matters is the conclusion that
真正重要的结论是
a convolution between two Gaussians is itself another Gaussian.
两个高斯函数之间的卷积  本身仍然是一个高斯函数
If you were to go back and reintroduce all of the constants for a normal distribution
如果你回去重新加上正态分布中的常数
with a mean 0 and an arbitrary standard deviation, σ,
平均值依然是 0   标准差 σ 可以是任意值
essentially identical reasoning will lead to the same √2 factor
那么用同样的方法推导  也会得到这个 √2 因子
that shows up in the exponent and out front
它出现在指数  以及前面的倍数中
and it leads to the conclusion that
我们由此可以得出结论
the convolution between two such normal distributions
两个标准差为 σ 的正态分布的卷积
is another normal distribution with a standard deviation √2 σ.
是另一个正态分布  标准差为 √2σ
If you haven't computed a lot of convolutions before,
如果你之前没有算过很多卷积的话
it's worth emphasizing this is a very special result.
那我要强调  这个结论其实是非常特殊的
Almost always, you end up with a completely different kind of function.
你几乎总是会得到另一个不同的函数
But here, there's a sort of stability to the process.
但正态分布的卷积具有某种稳定性
Also, for those of you who enjoy exercises, I'll leave one up on the screen
我还给想练手的观众朋友们  留了一道题目
for how you would handle the case of two different standard deviations.
看看你如何应对两个标准差不同的情形
Still, some of you might be raising your hands and saying,
话说回来  有人就要举手说了
"What's the big deal?"
“这有什么大不了的”
I mean, when you first heard the question
你看  当你一开始听到这个问题
"What do you get when you add two normally distributed random variables?"
“两个正态随机变量相加  是什么呢”
you probably even guessed that
你甚至可以猜到
the answer should be another normally distributed variable.
答案应该是另一个正态分布的变量
After all, what else is it going to be?
毕竟  还能有什么其他答案呢
Normal distributions are supposedly quite common, so, why not?
正态分布都这么普遍了  还能是啥
And you could even say that this should follow from the Central Limit Theorem.
你甚至会说  得出这个结论的依据是中心极限定理
But that would have it all backwards.
不过这就本末倒置了
First of all, the supposed ubiquity of normal distributions
首先 「正态分布无所不在」这个说法  多少有点夸张
is often a little exaggerated.
But to the extent that they do come up, it is because of the Central Limit Theorem.
正态分布的出现  通常是伴随着中心极限定理的
But it would be cheating to say
但错误而违心的说法就是
the Central Limit Theorem implies this result
“中心极限定理暗示着这个答案的存在”
because this computation we just did is the reason that
因为  先有了我们前面的计算  才能解释
the function at the heart of the Central Limit Theorem is a Gaussian in the first place
为什么中心极限定理的核心函数是高斯函数
and not some other function.
而不是其他函数
We've talked all about the Central Limit Theorem before
我们前面讨论过中心极限定理
but essentially it says if you repeatedly add copies of a random variable to itself,
简而言之  如果你重复相加同一个随机变量
which mathematically looks like
数学上像是对同一个概率密度函数多次重复求卷积
repeatedly computing convolutions against a given distribution,
then after appropriate shifting and rescaling,
那么经过合适的平移和缩放
the tendency is always to approach a normal distribution.
结果总会趋近于正态分布
Technically, there's a small assumption -
严格地说  这里应该有个小假设：
the distribution you start with can't have infinite variants
初始分布的方差不能是无穷大
but it's a relatively soft assumption.
不过这个假设是挺容易满足的
The magic is that for a huge category of initial distributions,
神奇的是  对于很大一类的初始分布
this process of adding a whole bunch of random variables drawn from that distribution
从该分布中取很多随机变量并相加的这个过程
always tends towards this one universal shape - a Gaussian.
总会趋近于这个万有的形状  高斯函数
One common approach to proving this theorem involves two separate steps.
证明该定理的一个常用手法是  分两步走
The first step is to show that
第一步是要证明
for all the different finite variants distributions you might start with,
对于任意有限方差的初始分布
there exists a single universal shape
存在某个万有的形状
that this process of repeated convolutions tends towards.
其为重复卷积的过程的极限
This step is actually pretty technical.
说实话  这一步需要一些技巧
It goes a little beyond what I want to talk about here.
有点超出了我想讨论的范围
You often use objects called Moment-generating function
这通常要用到一个工具  叫做“矩母函数”
that gives you a very abstract argument that there must be some universal shape
然后很抽象地去论证  必然有这样一个万有形状
but it doesn't make any claim about what that particular shape is,
不过这并不能说明  这个具体的形状是什么
just that everything in this big family
只能说明  一大类函数中的每一个
is tending towards a single point in the space of distributions.
都会收敛到分布空间中唯一的一点
So then step number two is what we just showed in this video -
因此  接下来的第二步  就是前面视频的部分
prove that the convolution of two Gaussians gives another Gaussian.
证明两个高斯函数的卷积  依然是高斯函数
What that means is that as you apply this process of repeated convolutions,
这意味着  当你进行重复卷积的操作
a Gaussian doesn't change. It's a fixed point.
高斯函数将保持不变  是一个不动点
So, the only thing it can approach is itself
它就只能逼近自己
and since it's one member in this big family of distributions
并且  它也是这个分布族中的一员
all of which must be tending towards a single universal shape,
而每一员都趋近于同一个万有形状
it must be that universal shape.
因此  高斯函数正是那个万有形状
I mentioned at the start
我一开始就提到
how this calculation, step two, is something that you can do directly
第二步的这个计算  是可以直接做的
just symbolically with the definitions
单纯形式化地用定义就行
but one of the reasons I'm so charmed by a geometric argument
但我之所以如此着迷于这个几何证明
that leverages the rotational symmetry of this graph
并妙用图像的旋转对称性
is that it directly connects to a few things that we've talked about on this channel before.
是因为  它能直接地联系上我们频道前面提到的内容
For example, the Herschel-Maxwell derivation of a Gaussian,
例如  赫歇尔-麦克斯韦对高斯分布的推导
which essentially says that you can view this rotational symmetry
说的是  你可以认为旋转对称性
as the defining feature of the distribution.
恰好刻画了正态分布的
That it locks you into this e^(-x²) form.
分布函数必须为 e 的 -x² 次方的形式
And also as an added bonus,
另一个附加的好处是
it connects to the classic proof for why π shows up in the formula.
这与「为何正态分布公式有 π」的经典证明  存在关联
Meaning we now have a direct line
我们这条直接线索
between the presence and mystery of that π and the Central Limit Theorem.
可以把 π 出现之谜  与中心极限定理联系起来
Also on a recent patreon post, the channel supporter Daksha Vaid-Kwinter
在最近的一条 Patreon 帖子中  资助人达刹·维德-昆特
brought my attention to a completely different approach I hadn't seen before
向我提到一个我没见过的全新证法
which leverages the use of entropy
这个证法利用了熵  作为证明工具
and again, for the theoretically curious among you,
对理论层面有所好奇的观众们
I'll leave some links in the description.
我会在评论区留下参考链接
By the way, if you want to stay up to date with new videos
插一句  如果你想追上最新视频
and also any other projects that I put out there like the Summer of Math Exposition,
以及其他项目  例如夏季数学博览会SoME
there is a mailing list.
欢迎订阅邮件列表
It's relatively new
才刚开始弄
and I'm pretty sparing about only posting what I think people will enjoy.
我会精选我觉得大家会喜欢的内容来发
Usually, I try not to be too promotional at the end of videos these days
近来我在视频结尾尽量不太会打广告
but if you are interested in following the work that I do,
但如果你希望关注我在做的工作
this is probably one of the most enduring ways to do so.
订阅这个邮件列表也许是最持久的方式了